NARRATOR: Summer. 2015.
Shark attacks in the United States have reached their limit.
911: What did you say? A shark?
WOMAN: She ripped a man's arm off!
NARRATOR: Just in the course of one summer,
Sharks off the coast of the Carolinas attacked
unexpectedly to 11 people.
WOMAN: True. MAN: Tore off his arm.
NARRATOR: While the attacks were making headlines.
WOMAN: You don't see anyone swimming these days!
NARRATOR: Experts are wondering: What's causing this sudden outbreak?
GREG: There must be something that triggers it.
NARRATOR: Now, two scientists from totally different worlds
They look for the answer.
They dive into waters full of sharks.
JOE: You guys are completely crazy!
NARRATOR: To test his revolutionary theory.
GREG: He's coming so fast! He's fast!
NARRATOR: Such attacks could be weather-related.
If true, it could change our knowledge about sharks and rides.
on the beach, forever.
The Bahamas.
Join a veteran shark scientist.
GREG: If we can use the weather to indicate what sharks do,
We could predict whether a shark attack will happen or not!
And that would be wonderful!
NARRATOR: And a very experienced meteorologist.
JOE: I'm excited to work with Greg and show him that my hypothesis is correct:
that wind and weather have an effect on where sharks are located.
NARRATOR: And you might discover something very important.
It may sound crazy that the weather can help predict the likelihood of an attack.
of shark, but the science behind the theory is real.
JOE: My name is Joe Merchant, I'm a meteorologist with the National Weather Service.
My goal is to protect lives and property.
I am trained to deal with storm warnings and hurricane watch,
hurricane warnings, including tornado warnings.
I've actually had to chase tornadoes.
Look at that!
NARRATOR: Sharks weren't part of Joe's forecast.
until the tsunami of attacks in 2015 caught their attention.
JOE: There were 11 shark attacks off the coast of the Carolinas.
There I began to observe the weather.
I observed the weather during these attacks and saw that there was a pattern.
I decided to call the only shark expert I had read about: Dr. Skomal.
GREG: My name is Greg Skomal, I'm a biologist.
And affiliated with the Massachusetts Division of Marine Fisheries.
I have studied sharks for over 30 years.
I have focused especially on the great white shark.
When Joes called me I had all these ideas about
how climate change patterns might influence
to an animal that lives in the water.
It started to make a little sense.
NARRATOR: Now, Joe teams up with Greg to test his bold new theory.
Joe believes that the winds attract small marine life closer to the shore.
These small prey attract large predators.
Which in turn attracts the largest predators: sharks.
Follow this food chain that the wind brings,
This is what drives sharks towards the shore, close to swimmers.
JOE: Taking what we know from the wind forecast,
We can use this information and put it into a model
and thus predict where a shark attack might occur.
So that on a Sunday afternoon, if a family goes to the beach,
can have a very clear idea of where the sharks are.
NARRATOR: To test Joe's theory they want to observe two different species,
frequently involved in human attacks: tiger sharks, and bull sharks.
There are many of them here in the Bahamas.
First, the tigers.
GREG: Here we go!
Joe, we'll head towards Tiger Beach, which is up here. JOE: Okay.
GREG: Yeah, right at the edge of this bench.
Uh, very deep water to the west, shallow water to the east,
and there are lots of tiger sharks here.
NARRATOR: Their mission: to tag sharks with tracking devices.
to observe whether they respond to the changing climate.
But it won't be easy.
Tiger sharks are some of the most formidable hunters in the ocean.
Predators with large, flat noses that can measure up to
more than 5 meters and weigh almost a ton.
Tiger sharks are named for their dark vertical lines.
And they project their colors across the tropical and subtropical waters of the world.
They have an almost limitless diet, ranging from natural prey, such as fish,
seals and birds.
Even human waste, such as car license plates and tires.
This undiscerning palate sometimes also includes people.
Leaving them second only to great white sharks in human attacks.
And the perfect species to test the theory
Joe's claim that wind plays a role in attacks.
CAPTAIN: We're here, we need to anchor here.
WOMAN: Understood.
JOE: I've never seen a tiger shark before.
And this is incredible.
I think you can see my arm bristling right now.
I'll definitely let Greg take it from here.
I think I'll be watching the weather on the boat.
I don't want to let go!
GREG: Yeah, this is a good place.
Without sharks you can't study them, so step one, complete!
JOE: Yes. GREG: I like it.
NARRATOR: Step two: Greg gets into the water with the tiger sharks.
and mark them with monitoring equipment.
GREG: We're going to attach this camera system to the shark's fin.
It's a device that has all kinds of instrumentation in there,
that measures temperature and depth.
And it also has a camera system, so we can get a look
of the shark about what is happening underwater.
And the other instruments on it indicate the 3 movements of the shark
to be able to know where it is going, how fast it is moving,
up and down in the water column, in relation to temperature and depth.
We will be able to correlate this behavior with the weather as it changes.
and the wind increases, we will know what the shark is doing
in relation to climate changes.
The key will be to slide it over the dorsal fin, right here.
Let's pull the trigger, bang! We're going.
It won't hurt the shark, it just holds onto the fin,
I bet he won't even react.
It sounds easy, but I have to get as close as I can, then align it,
and wait for him to cooperate.
Many things have to turn out excellent.
NARRATOR: Tigers aren't the only predators in these waters.
Bull and lemon sharks are never far away.
Especially when it's mealtime.
GRANT: We have so many sharks here that we have to try to keep them
a little far from us.
When you have so many sharks in the same area,
they start competing with each other.
NARRATOR: The team is racing against the clock to complete their mission:
a storm is approaching the islands.
JOE: We're starting to see a little bit of instability thanks to that big storm.
It's a sign that things are going to change here very soon.
NARRATOR: Joe thinks the storm will hit tomorrow afternoon.
JOE: The faster you get in the water and tag a shark, the better.
And we'll be able to see how the shark reacts to the storm system.
You guys are completely crazy!
GREG: All right, I'm going after them!
NARRATOR: The lemon sharks arrive immediately.
It's a shark storm.
JOE: Okay, now I'm going to put this in.
Testing: one, two, three.
I wanted to check that you were okay down there.
GREG: I'm fine, Joe.
JOE: Tell me what you're watching?
GREG: I see a tiger! I see a tiger!
NARRATOR: Now, Greg needs to get close enough to tag him.
JOE: Greg? This is Joe, can you hear me?
I don't hear anything.
GREG: He's coming very fast! Very fast!
I'm having a hard time marking it.
Let's go. Let's go.
GREG: I see a tiger! I see a tiger!
I'm having a hard time marking it.
NARRATOR: Shark biologist Greg Skomal and meteorologist Joe Merchant,
They try to test a new revolutionary theory
which could help predict shark attacks:
They believe that sharks react to the weather, and that certain winds can
take sharks to hunt near the coast,
which causes shark attacks on swimmers.
JOE: There are many!
GREG: We look forward to seeing how changes in the climate above the water influence
in the behavior of sharks underwater.
NARRATOR: Greg must first tie up a complex system of cameras and computers
to the dorsal fin of one of these tiger sharks.
The forecast down here is for high pressure.
Blood pressure.
GREG: He's got Grant's fin!
He's got Grant's dive bag!
Oh no, he's attacking the bait box!
NARRATOR: Then another aggressive species approaches and takes action.
GREG: Oh, a hammerhead shark appeared out of nowhere!
JOE: Greg, there are a lot of sharks swimming around you!
GREG: There's complete chaos here!
(music)
Damn!
There are too many! Let's go up!
NARRATOR: Greg's first attempt to tag a shark was too dangerous.
JOE: Did you make it? GREG: No. They were
JOE: No? GREG: Damn!
It's frustrating! We came close, three or four times.
GRANT: That tiger shark came really close!
As soon as that bait went down to the bottom!
GREG: You were the most popular guy on campus!
GRANT: Yeah, they were a little too close for my liking.
JOE: At one point, it seemed like some of the other sharks
they were getting in each other's way a little.
GREG: The hammerhead shark kept getting in the way.
I never thought there would be so many sharks.
We have to get in there and try again. JOE: Okay.
I hope we can tag the shark very quickly.
because that great storm is approaching,
These are the conditions I would have expected for a shark attack.
NARRATOR: Joe anticipates the storm will bring winds similar to those
that occurred during the spate of attacks in the Carolinas in 2015.
JOE: Greg, they're coming in!
GREG: The tiger is coming!
I'll try to mark it!
Come here, come here!
I got it! I did it! Finally! Yuhuuu.
JOE: They did it! They did it! Good!
(laughs)
Genial.
GREG: Yeah, we got one! GRANT: Yeah?
GREG: We were late. One finally came over, behaved himself.
We tried, the clamp got stuck.
Then we came back, tried again, bang!
We did it, great it was great.
JOE: Excellent! GREG: Yes.
Now the experiment begins! It's what we wanted.
NARRATOR: All thanks to the tiger's new gadget.
JOE: It means we're now going to be able to combine this new information with the weather data.
And let's hope we see exactly what I think is happening:
that the weather may be playing a role in the events
that lead to those shark attacks.
GREG: Every second it's collecting dozens of data points.
JOE: Right.
GREG: So the more seconds you're out, minutes, hours,
we will get more information.
But we have to get it back!
That's the key!
Having tagged the shark is the first step.
Collecting data and literally collecting
thousands of information points every minute,
We will get a lot of this research, but only if we recover it.
These are sharks capable of swimming hundreds of kilometers.
And it is also a very big ocean.
NARRATOR: The tiger shark's apparatus will take off
in about 5 hours and will float to the surface.
This is when the device's light will activate, allowing the team to track it.
GREG: It could be 3 meters away or 32 kilometers away.
So we need to make sure that all the technology takes us to the right place.
We have to locate it using satellite receivers
and high frequency.
But there is always the possibility of never finding it.
NARRATOR: Especially with the storm that's about to hit Tiger Beach soon.
GREG: The longer he stays with the fish, the more information we'll have.
It's very exciting.
We have the shark swimming in the sea,
He has the data collector and camera on his back!
I think we should come here every hour, during the night.
It should emerge in 4 or 5 hours, so we have time, but I want to see it.
NARRATOR: The new dawn shows no sign of the device,
but reveals a growing threat.
JOE: It's a funnel cloud. That one over there is.
It's a sign that things are changing now.
NARRATOR: The storm Joe predicted is heading straight for them.
JOE: You can see all those clouds gathering over there.
GREG: It's raining a lot! JOE: Yes.
So this is the beginning of the end of our time on the boat.
GREG: That's very disturbing!
(laughs)
GREG: He knows something I don't, it's good to have a meteorologist on board.
NARRATOR: But that big storm is also a great opportunity.
JOE: We'll be able to see how that shark responds.
in the face of changing weather conditions.
NARRATOR: Now, they just need to find that device
as soon as it comes off!
Finally, a sign.
GREG: Do you have it?
ANNABELLE: Asi es.
NARRATOR: The device emerged.
GREG: We're close to this thing!
Stop! There it is! I've got it! I see it!
At 1 o'clock, arriving at 2! ANNABELLE: Yes! Of course.
GREG: 'Now it's 3 o'clock!
JOE: I see it too! ANNABELLE: There.
GREG: Perfect!
Good work, Annabelle.
NARRATOR: But Greg isn't the only one behind the device.
JOE: Is that a tiger? GREG: Yeah.
Well, I'll go for it!
JOE: Amazing!
GREG: I got it. JOE: You're crazy.
NARRATOR: Now, you just have to go back.
JOE: Well done!
GREG: I got it back.
JOE: I would have let him win.
I would have been more than happy to let that shark win.
GREG: This experiment is useless if we don't get it back, it's very important!
We're already halfway there. Let's see what's in it!
It's like opening Christmas presents!
JOE: I'm really excited to review the information.
But it's time to go because there's a big storm coming in a few hours.
And it's better for us to go.
Tiger Beach NARRATOR: They return to the lab
in Eleuthera to download the information
and see if the shark reacted to the changing winds.
GREG: Let's take a look.
JOE: Amazing. GREG: Now you're the one! The shark!
JOE: I try, I really do. Oh!
GREG: There's another tiger shark! JOE: Wow.
GREG: Isn't that great? JOE: No way! Wow!
GREG: He's following another tiger.
Very close up. It's wonderful!
JOE: This footage is amazing because now I can see what the shark
does underwater and how it behaves naturally.
GREG: He's just swimming.
It is now halfway down the water column.
NARRATOR: Joe records his information to see if there is a correlation
between climate change and shark behavior.
And of course there is.
GREG: Here we have a dramatic change in behavior.
He dives twice.
JOE: So this was, it was right before the big storm
that made us leave tiger beach.
GREG: They retreat before the storm hits, so they sense something.
NARRATOR: Apparently sharks react to the change in climate.
Now, it's time to find out if the right conditions
of the wind will bring them closer to the coast.
For that, they will tag a bull shark.
GREG: We want to really see how much these coastal winds influence the behavior
of sharks near land.
and the species we will do it with will be bull sharks.
It is another shark that has been involved in unprovoked attacks on people.
It is considered one of the most dangerous sharks on the planet.
NARRATOR: Bull sharks are named for their short, flat snout,
and for their aggressive tendencies: they often headbutt their prey before attacking it.
Bull sharks do not grow as large as tiger sharks, but they can reach a length of more than
3 meters and weighing up to 200 kilograms are formidable predators that will eat
virtually anything they see, including crabs, turtles and other sharks.
Which could explain the extraordinary strength of its bite, kilo for kilo,
the strongest of all the sharks in the sea.
They often enter shallow waters, where they find people.
Greg and Joe think the bulls may be chasing minnows.
that approach the coast under certain wind conditions.
JOE: Hopefully, we'll find some kind of change in the shark's behavior.
in relation to the wind.
NARRATOR: Greg has a lead on a bull shark hotspot:
a nearby marina.
GREG: I'm told bull sharks come here daily,
so I hope I can tag one of these underwater animals.
NARRATOR: In this murky place, Greg will put his life in danger.
GREG: Bull sharks are very effective hunters and usually hunt
in areas with poor visibility, and that's exactly what we have here.
These conditions are not optimal.
As you can see, the water is cloudy. JOE: True.
GREG: It's even worse when you get in the water. JOE: Yeah.
GREG: My visibility will be very limited and sharks come from any direction.
direction, so I need you to be my eyes, okay?
JOE: Of course.
GREG: I have to admit I'm worried about getting in the water with bull sharks.
I'll definitely keep my eyes open.
JOE: Tell me what you see?
GREG: Damn.
JOE: Greg is in the water, and I'm actually here for safety,
to be in communication with him.
Staying alert and hoping we see a bull shark.
We try to tag a bull shark, and if we succeed,
we will be able to obtain the information we need.
NARRATOR: Information that may prove Joe's theory, that under certain
coastal wind conditions, like those we had today,
could affect the behavior of sharks,
bringing them closer to the coast and closer to us.
Right now, Greg is in bull territory.
JOE: Greg, it looks pretty bad from this spot.
Can you see anything?
GREG: Damn, I can't see anything down here!
Wait! What's that? Is that a bull shark coming toward me?
I'm going out. I'm going out.
This isn't working.
The visibility in this place is horrible.
We'll have to do something different.
If there was a shark there, not only would I not be able to see it,
but there would be no way to mark it.
And I'm not comfortable being with sharks.
in places where I don't see them!
I see the statistics, and I know, I'm sure that they are very good in terms of hunting,
and catch other species in shallow, murky waters,
and that's what we have here.
We'll do plan B: try to tag them from the dock.
The best way to do it is to throw fish, blood, honestly, parts into the water,
and start attracting them with lots of bait.
And once we have the bull shark's attention, lure them here,
and thus mark them.
JOE: I'd rather go looking for sharks now than watch you cut that thing.
GREG: have you heard?
These weathermen, huh? Come on!
JOE: I'm a meteorologist, Greg!
GREG: So we're hoping to attract a shark. JOE: Yeah.
GREG: And when we do, we might have to hook him.
JOE: I expect the winds to shift a little more to the south today.
So I think our chances are increasing to score one of them.
NARRATOR: The storm is out at sea, but its effects are still being felt.
JOE: The anemometer is in use, collecting data.
GREG: He's collecting too much, with the wind the way it is.
JOE: Considering what we know about wind forecasts,
We can take this information and put it into a model and thus predict
where a shark attack could occur.
And I think these forecasts can be very valuable for beach communities,
especially where people are using the water recreationally.
GREG: Joe is basically saying that atmospheric conditions
will direct what happens beneath the surface.
And of course I believe him: the atmosphere and water are deeply connected.
We have a lot of activity here.
We have a lot of remoras, which are usually attached to sharks,
so I hope the sharks are close and these remoras just
take off and take advantage of the bait we threw into the water.
Come on, sharks, where are you?
NARRATOR: Suddenly, a lemon shark.
GREG: Did you see it?
NARRATOR: As the sun sets, Greg takes the opportunity to score.
to a different shallow-water shark.
GREG: Another very common species around Eleuthera are lemon sharks.
It is a coastal species, of shallow waters.
And if there is one fish that is going to be affected in any way by climate changes,
I suspect it's going to be one that lives in very shallow water.
Is that the one over there? GRANT: Yes.
GREG: All right! That's it!
There's the lemon!
Maybe we'll try to tag this lemon shark.
JOE: Yes, it is veils!
GREG: We have a lot of bait on that line and what the guys do
is trying to attract that lemon closer.
NARRATOR: They tie the end of the rope to a bright orange buoy.
If the lemon shark bites the bait, it will pull the buoy with it,
and will allow the team to easily locate the shark,
tire him out and then mark him.
GREG: There's something there! JOE: Yes.
GREG: It could be him!
There it is! JOE: Oh!
GREG: There it is!
JOE: Left! Yes! GREG: Find it!
Be the ball, Danny!
JOE: Come on, come on!
-Do you have it? WOMAN: Yes.
GREG: Watch out! JOE: Hook him up! Good!
GREG: Watch out!
Watch the ball. Don't stop watching the ball.
NARRATOR: The shark takes the buoy.
GREG: Good. JOE: Brendan!
Curse!
I can't believe it! GREG: What did I tell you, man?
Bottom of the ninth, 2 cars down, we're losing by a run.
We've got the lemon shark in that ball over there,
He took one of the baits and we hoped to tire him out.
When he gets tired, we'll bring him to the side of the boat, and tag him.
But we have to move!
That's it, ready. Here we go! We're going to do well!
Do you have it?
Yes, we see it. Okay, who's driving?
NARRATOR: After days of trying to tag a shallow-water shark,
The team's perseverance finally pays off.
GREG: We have a lemon shark here that we've already hooked and we're going to tag.
JOE: When they hooked the lemon, it had a little buoy that started pulling.
It's like in the movie "Jaws."
NARRATOR: It's the crucial first step in testing Joe's theory.
That winds, like tonight's, affect the shark's behavior,
taking it closer to the coast to hunt.
And closer to us.
JOE: We have a strong front that's going to be moving northwest.
So. If we can tag the shark once and for all,
we will be able to see its behavior as the front approaches.
My skin is goosebumps
This is amazing!
It's heading to
goes to the entrance!
GREG: No way! I don't like him running.
DUNCAN: Around those piles!
GREG: Damn! That's bad!
NARRATOR: The slippery lemon moves
through the maze of boats in the place.
You put yourself at risk by hooking your buoy around a pile or propeller.
GREG: Right under the boat. GRANT: It's behind the boat.
GREG: Damn! Looks like, I think it's stuck there.
GRANT: Neutral! Let him go. Let him go.
GREG: Don't stop him. Good.
DUNCAN: Remember they can bite their own tails!
GREG: Yes.
GRANT: Come on. Neutral! GREG: Neutral.
Got it! Got it, here we go.
NARRATOR: But just when he's about to reach it.
BRENDAN: Oh, I can't believe it.
GREG: He spit it out! Look at that!
He had everything inside, he had everything in his mouth.
He bit it all! Wow!
Damn! It didn't catch.
JOE: Why are they coming back?
It can't be! What happened?
GREG: That fish got off the hook. Bye.
He left without the device.
We had a lemon shark hooked and it dragged the ball all over the harbor,
so it looked like it was pretty hooked
and we were ready to tag this fish
and we brought it closer to the boat and the hook came out.
Bang! It's over. Goodbye.
Well, let's finish for today and we'll try again tomorrow.
Tomorrow will be another day
NARRATOR: Back on the sports field,
refocus their attention on the area of the alpha predator: the bull shark.
JOE: Greg, I have one that looks like a cat.
It's even faster than the cat shark.
I really don't know what it is.
GREG: Tell me, what color is it?
JOE: It's actually grayer. Not as brown as cats. You know what I mean?
GREG: Really? Is it big? JOE: Yeah, it's big!
GREG: Really?
Well, bring the device and the pole.
JOE: All right.
You'll definitely be able to score this one, Greg.
GREG: Are you serious?
JOE: Still, he's hanging around here.
GREG: Joe Merch, attention. Ready for action.
It could be a bull shark. That's what we wanted. See how it moves?
Totally different. JOE: Yes.
GREG: Oh my god, I'll have to go down and try that.
It's not going to be easy. JOE: Can you do it?
GREG: All right, Joe! Let's go. JOE: Are you okay?
Okay. Watch out.
GREG: You have to be patient.
Okay, I'll try it now.
Here it comes, coming closer, there it is. Let's go.
JOE: Are you okay? Okay.
GREG: I'm going to try it now.
Here it comes, it's coming.
I did it. JOE: Did you do it?
GREG: Yes. I did.
(laughs)
I have it.
JOE: I don't think so.
GREG: beautiful.
JOE: He turned left, you can't see it anymore.
GREG: Well, maybe it's just coming out of the port, and I think that's great.
Good! Great!
Now we have to wait.
We've been working here for 3 days and nothing, nothing, nothing.
And suddenly, boom!
Now we can start this experiment!
JOE: We put the device on the bull and if it can stay on the shark,
then we will get a large data set.
NARRATOR: They have all the elements they need to prove their theory,
that the wind affects the shark's behavior.
A device on a bull shark and a strong northwest wind.
JOE: I really hope we can get the device back from the bull shark because everything
what I believe leads to a shark attack is happening right now.
NARRATOR: Two and a half hours later, the device detaches itself from the bull shark.
and they go in search of action.
GREG: At 11 o'clock!
Here we go! Perfect! We got it!
NARRATOR: They return to the lab to analyze the information and material.
JOE: If we can see the changes in the weather from below
of the surface with the camera, then we could truly see,
in real time the change in behavior of a shark.
GREG: I'm excited to see this!
I have the data and the videos here. Okay.
JOE: I've been looking at the satellite and radar information from when we marked
to the shark and you can see that it's a nice breezy day.
GREG: Everything appears immediately.
JOE: Sure.
GREG: You know, it's actually headed in the right direction.
Crossing over these sponges, some soft coral, a whole school of small fish
and he is not interested in them.
JOE: And the wind is changing.
NARRATOR: The wind shifts, disturbing the flora in the shallow waters.
and the small prey that live in it.
GREG: Now see this: it's going towards a shallow sandy plain.
Looks like it's going straight for the surface, right? JOE: Yeah!
NARRATOR: The shark's behavior does seem to fit Joe's theory.
The wind brings the smaller fish, and that brings the sharks.
GREG: We know there are smaller fish in the harbor,
I saw some of those when I was down there for a very short time.
JOE: You can actually see the clouds forming right above where he's swimming.
GREG: So you're mixing up their habitats, to maybe,
see what might be happening in them to find possible
food and so eat.
NARRATOR: Joe's crazy idea that shark attacks may be linked
with the weather, it may not be so far-fetched after all.
JOE: It's amazing.
I think coastal winds lead to a food chain response.
which eventually brings a shark close to the shore, where the people are.
GREG: I think there is definitely an influence of weather on behavior.
of the fish beneath the surface.
Perhaps a pattern will emerge and we will predict
the behavior of sharks.
JOE: So that, on a Sunday afternoon, if a family goes to the beach,
can at least get an idea of where the sharks are.
NARRATOR: Meteorologists may soon be able to say:
sunny with strong winds and 80 percent
probability of sharks.
GREG: It's going to take a lot of animals and a lot of information, but I think it's a good start.
JOE: Yes! (laughs)
Subtitles created by SubTitlePro LLC